Chapter 1. An unexpected party.
In a hole in the ground there lived a hobbit. Not a nasty, dirty, wet hole
filled with the ends of worms in an uzzy smell, nor yet a dry, bare, sandy hole
with nothing in it to sit down on or to eat. It was a hobbit hole, and that
means comfort. It had a perfectly round door like a port hole painted green with
a shiny yellow brass knob in the exact middle. The door opened onto a
tube-shaped hole like a tunnel, a very comfortable tunnel without smoke, with
panled walls and floors tiled and carpeted, provided with polished chairs
and lots and lots of pegs for hats and coats.
The hobbit was fond of visitors. The tunnel wound on and on going fairly but
not quite straight into the side of a hill. The hill, as all the people for
many miles round called it, and many little round doors opened out of it,
first on one side and then on another.
No going upstairs for the hobbit.
Bedrooms, bathrooms, cellars, pantries, lots of these wardrobes. He had whole
rooms devoted to clothes, kitchens, dining rooms, all were on the same floor
and indeed on the same passage. The best rooms were all on the left hand side
going in, for these were the only ones to have windows, deep set round windows
looking over his garden and meadows beyond sloping down to the river. This
hobbit was a very wellto-do hobbit, and his name was Baggins. The Bagginses had
lived in the neighborhood of the hill for time out of mind, and people
considered them very respectable, not only because most of them were rich, but
also because they never had any adventures or did anything unexpected.
You could tell what a Baggins would say on any question without the bother of
asking him. This is a story of how a Baggins had an adventure and found
himself doing and saying things altogether unexpected.
He may have lost the neighbors respect, but he gained well. You will see whether
he gained anything in the end. The mother of our particular hobbit. What is
a hobbit? I suppose hobbits need some description nowadays since they have
become rare and shy of the big people as they call us. They are or were a little
people about half our height and smaller than the bearded dwarves. Hobbits have
no beards. There is little or no magic about them except the ordinary everyday
sort which helps them to disappear quietly and quickly when large stupid
folk like you and me come blundering along making a noise like elephants
which they can hear a mile off. They are inclined to be fat in the stomach. They
dress in bright colors, chiffly green and yellow. Wear no shoes because their
feet grow natural leathery soles and thick warm brown hair like the stuff on
their heads which is curly. Have long clever brown fingers, good-natured
faces, and laugh deep fruity laughs especially after dinner which they have
twice a day when they can get it. Now
you know enough to go on with. As I was saying, the mother of this hobbit of
Bilbel Baggin, that is, was the famous Belelladana Tuk, one of the three
remarkable daughters of the old Tuk, head of the hobbits who lived across the
water, the small river that ran at the foot of the hill. It was often said in
other families that long ago one of the Tuk ancestors must have taken a fairy
wife. That was of course absurd, but certainly there was still something not
entirely Hobbitlike about them, and once in a while members of the Tuk clan would
go and have adventures. They discreetly disappeared, and the family hushed it
up, but the fact remained that the Tuks were not as respectable as the Baggins,
though they were undoubtedly richer. Not that Belladana Tuk ever had any
adventures after she became Mrs. Bongo Baggins. Bumbo, that was Bilbo's father,
built the most luxurious hobbit hole for her, and partly with her money that was
to be found either under the hill or over the hill or across the water. And
there they remained to the end of their days. Still, it is probable that Bilbo,
her only son, although he looked and behaved exactly like a second addition
of his solid and comfortable father, got something a bit queer in his makeup from
the to side, something that only waited for a chance to come out. The chance
never arrived until Bilbo Baggins was grown up, being about 50 years old or
so, and living in the beautiful Hobbit hole built by his father, which I have
just described for you, until he had, in fact, apparently settled down immovably.
By some curious chance one morning long ago in the quiet of the world, when
there was less noise and more green, and the hobbits were still numerous and
prosperous, and Bilbo Baggins was standing at his door after breakfast,
smoking an enormous long wooden pipe that reached nearly down to his woolly
toes, neatly brushed. Jandalf came by.
If you had heard only a quarter of what I have heard about him, and I have only
heard very little of all there is to hear, you would be prepared for any sort
of remarkable tale. Tales and adventure sprouted up all over the place wherever
he went, in the most extraordinary fashion. He had not been down that way
under the hill for ages and ages, not since his friend the old Tuk died, in
fact, and the hobbits had almost forgotten what he looked like. He had
been away over the hill and across the water on businesses of his own, since
they were all small hobbit boys and hobbit girls. All that the unsuspecting
Bilbo saw that morning was an old man with a staff. He had a tall pointed blue
hat, a long gray cloak, a silver scarf over which his long white beard hung
down below his waist, and immense black boots. "Good morning," said Bilbo, and
he meant it. The sun was shining and the grass was very green. But Gandalf looked
at him from under long bushy eyebrows that stuck out further than the brim of
his shady hat. "What do you mean?" he said. "Do you wish me a good morning, or
mean that it is a good morning, whether I want it or not, or that you feel good
this morning, or that it is a morning to be good on?" all of them at once, said
Bilbo. And a very fine morning for a pipe of tobacco out of doors into the
bargain. If you have a pipe about you, sit down and have a fill of mine.
There's no hurry. We have all the day before us." Then Bilbo sat down on a
seat by his door, crossed his legs, and blew out a beautiful gray ring of smoke
that sailed up into the air without breaking, and floated away over the
hill. "Very pretty," said Gandalf. But I have no time to blow smoke rings this
morning. I am looking for someone to share in an adventure that I am
arranging, and it's very difficult to find anyone.
I should think so in these parts. We are plain quiet folk and have no use for
adventures. Nasty, disturbing, uncomfortable things make you late for
dinner. I can't think what anybody sees in them, said our Mr. wagons and stuck
one thumb behind his braces and blew out another even bigger smokering. Then he
took out his morning letters and began to read, pretending to take no more
notice of the old man. He had decided that he was not quite his sort and
wanted him to go away. But the old man did not move. He stood leaning on his
stick and gazing at the hobbit without saying anything till Bilbo got quite
uncomfortable and even a little cross.
Good morning, he said at last. We don't want any adventures here. Thank you. You
might try over the hill or across the water. By this he meant that the
conversation was at an end. What a lot of things you do use good morning for,
said Gandalf. Now you mean that you want to get rid of me and that it won't be
good till I move off. Not at all. Not at
all, my dear sir. Let me see. I don't think I know your name. Yes. Yes, my
dear sir, and I do know your name, Mr.
Bilbo Baggins. And you do know my name, though you don't remember that I belong
to it. I am Gandalf, and Gandalf means me. To think that I should have lived to
be good morninged by Belladon took son, as if I was selling buttons at the door.
Gandalf. Gandalf. Good gracious me. Not the wandering wizard that gave old took
a pair of magic diamond studs that fastened themselves and never came
undone till ordered. Not the fellow who used to tell such wonderful tales at
parties about dragons and goblins and giants and the rescue of princesses and
the unexpected luck of widows sons. Not the man that used to make such
particularly excellent fireworks. I remember those. Old Tok used to have
them on midsummer's eve. Splendid. They used to go up like great liies and
snapdragons and laburnums of fire and hang in the twilight all evening. You
will notice already that Mr. Baggins was not quite so prosy as he liked to
believe. Also that he was very fond of flowers. Dear me, he went on the Gandalf
who was responsible for so many quiet lads and lasses going off into the blue
for mad adventures. anything from climbing trees to visiting elves or
sailing in ships, sailing to other shores. Bless me, life used to be quite
inter. I mean, you used to upset things badly in these parts once upon a time. I
beg your pardon, but I had no idea you were still in business.
Where else should I be? said the wizard.
All the same, I am pleased to find you remember something about me. You seem to
remember my fireworks kindly at any rate, and that is not without hope.
Indeed, for your old grandfather took sake, and for the sake of poor
Belladonna, I will give you what you asked for. I beg your pardon. I haven't asked for anything.
Yes, you have twice now. My pardon, I give it you. In fact, I will go so far
as to send you on this adventure. Very amusing for me, very good for you, and
profitable, too. very likely if you ever get over it. Sorry, I don't want any
adventures. Thank you. Not today. Good morning, but please come to tea anytime
you like. Why not tomorrow? Come tomorrow. Goodbye. With that, the hobbit
turned and scuttled inside his round green door and shut it as quickly as he
dared, not to seem rude. Wizards, after all, are wizards. What on earth did I
ask him to te for? he said to himself as
he went to the pantry. He had only just had breakfast, but he thought a cake or
two and a drink of something would do him good after his fright. Gandalf, in
the meantime, was still standing outside the door and laughing long but quietly.
After a while, he stepped up and with the spike on his staff, scratched a
queer sign on the hobbit's beautiful green front door. Then he stroed away
just about the time when Bilbo was finishing his second cake and beginning
to think that he had escaped adventures very well. The next day he had almost
forgotten about Gandalf. He did not remember things very well unless he put
them down on his engagement tablet like this. Gandalf tea Wednesday. Yesterday
he had been too flustered to do anything of the kind. Just before tea time, there
came a tremendous ring on the front door bell, and then he remembered.
He rushed and put on the kettle and put out another cup and saucer and an extra
cake or two, and ran to the door. "I am so sorry to keep you waiting," he was
going to say when he saw that it was not
Gandalf at all. "It was a dwarf with a blue beard tucked into a golden belt and
very bright eyes under his dark green hood. As soon as the door was opened, he
pushed inside just as if he had been expected. He hung his hooded cloak on
the nearest peg. And Dwallin at your service, he said with a low bow. Bilbo
Baggins at yours, said the hobbit, too surprised to ask any questions for the
moment. When the silence that followed had become uncomfortable, he added, "I
am just about to take tea. Pray come and have some with me." A little stiff
perhaps, but he meant it kindly. And what would you do if an uninvited dwarf
came and hung his things up in your hall without a word of explanation?
They had not been at table long. In fact, they had hardly reached the third
cake when there came another even louder ring at the bell. "Excuse me," said the
hobbit, and off he went to the door. "So you have got here at last." That was
what he was going to say to Gandalf this time. But it was not Gandalf. Instead,
there was a very old-looking dwarf on the step with a white beard and a
scarlet hood, and he too hopped inside as soon as the door was opened, just as
if he had been invited. "I see they have begun to arrive already," he said when
he caught sight of Dwellan's green hood hanging up. He hung his red one next to
it. "And bail in at your service," he said with his hand on his breast. "Thank
you," said Bilbo with a gasp. It was not the correct thing to say, but they have
begun to arrive had flustered him badly.
He liked visitors, but he liked to know them before they arrived, and he
preferred to ask them himself. He had a horrible thought that the cakes might
run short, and then he, as the host, he knew his duty, and stuck to it, however
painful he might have to go without.
"Come along in and have some tea," he managed to say after taking a deep
breath. A little beer would suit me better if it is all the same to you, my
good sir, said Balon with the white beard. But I don't mind some cake seed
cake if you have any. Lots. Bilbo found himself answering to his own surprise,
and he found himself scuttling off too to the cellar to fill a pint beer mug,
and into a pantry to fetch two beautiful round seed cakes which he had baked that
afternoon for his after supper morsel.
When he got back, Balin and Dwallin were talking at the table like old friends.
As a matter of fact, they were brothers.
Bilbo plumped down the beer and the cake in front of them, when loud came a ring
at the bell again, and then another ring. Gandalf for certain this time, he
thought as he popped along the passage, but it was not. It was two more dwarves,
both with blue hoods, silver belts, and yellow beards, and each of them carried
a bag of tools and a spade. In they hopped, as soon as the door began to
open, Bilbo was hardly surprised at all.
"What can I do for you, my dwarves?" he said. "Killy at your service," said the
one. "And Feelely," added the other, and they both swept off their blue hoods and
bowed. at yours and your families, replied Bilbo, remembering his manners
this time. Dwell and bean here already, I see, said Killy. Let us join the fr.
Throng, thought Mr. Baggins. I don't like the sound of that. I really must
sit down for a minute and collect my wits and have a drink. He had only just
had a sip in the corner, while the four dwarves sat around the table and talked
about mines and gold and troubles with the goblins and the depradations of
dragons and lots of other things which he did not understand and did not want
to, for they sounded much too adventurous when, dinged on a ling dang,
his bell rang again, as if some naughty little hobbit boy was trying to pull the
handle off. Someone at the door, he said, blinking. Some four, I should say,
by the sound, said Philly. Besides, we saw them coming along behind us in the
distance. The poor little hobbit sat down in the hall and put his head in his
hands, and wondered what had happened, and what was going to happen, and
whether they would all stay to supper.
Then the bell rang again louder than ever, and he had to run to the door. It
was not for after all. It was wandering in the hole. He had hardly turned a knob
before they were all inside, bowing and saying, "At your service," one after
another. Dory, Nory, Aie, Owen, and Gloin were their names. And very soon
two purple hoods, a gray hood, a brown hood, and a white hood were hanging on
the pegs, and off they marched with their broad hands stuck in their golden
silver belts to join the others. Already it had almost become a throng. some
called for ale and some for porter and one for coffee and all of them for
cakes. So the hobbit was kept very busy for a while. A big jug of coffee had
just been set in the hearth. The seed cakes were gone and the drawers were
starting on a round of buttered scones when there came a loud knock. Not a ring
but a hard rat tat on the hobbit's beautiful green door. Somebody was
banging with a stick. Bilbo rushed along the passage, very angry, and altogether
bewildered and bewathered. This was the most awkward Wednesday he ever
remembered. He pulled open the door with a jerk, and they all fell in, one on top
of the other. More dwarves, four more, and there was Gandalf behind, leaning on
his staff and laughing. He had made quite a dent on the beautiful door. He
had also, by the way, knocked out the secret mark that he had put there the morning before.
Carefully, carefully, he said. It is not like you, Bilbo, to keep friends waiting
on the mat and then open the door like a pop gun. Let me introduce Bifur, Bofur,
Bomber, and especially Thoren.
At your service, said Bifur, Bofur and Bombbo standing in a row. Then they hung
up two yellow hoods and a pale green one, and also a sky blue one with a long
silver tassel. This last belonged to Thoren, an enormously important dwarf.
In fact, no other than the great Thoren Oak shield himself, who was not at all
pleased at falling flat on Bilbo's mat with Bifur Buffer and Bomber on top of
him. For one thing, Bomber was immensely fat and heavy. Thoren indeed was very
hotty and said nothing about service, but poor Mr. Baggin said he was sorry so
many times that at last he grunted, "Pray don't mention it." and stopped
frowning. "Now we are all here," said Gandalf, looking at the row of 13 hoods,
the best detachable party hoods, and his own hat hanging on the pegs. Quite a
merry gathering. I hope there is something left for the lay comers to eat
and drink. What's that? Tea? No, thank you. A little red wine, I think, for me.
And for me, said Doran. And raspberry jam and apple tight said by four. And
minced pies and cheese said Buffer.
And port pie and salad, said Bomber. And more cakes and ale and coffee if you
don't mind, called the other dwarves through the door. Put on a few eggs.
There's a good fellow. Gandalf called after him as the hobbit stumped off to
the pantries. And just bring out the cold chicken and pickles.
seems to know as much about the inside of my lardos as I do myself, thought Mr.
Baggins, who was feeling positively flumixed, and was beginning to wonder
whether a most wretched adventure had not come right into his house. By the
time he had got all the bottles and dishes and knives, and forks, and
glasses, and plates, and spoons, and things piled up on big trays, he was
getting very hot and red in the face, and annoyed. "Confosticate and be bother
these dwarves," he said aloud. Why don't they come and lend a hand? Lo and
behold, there stood Balin and Dwellan at the door of the kitchen, and Feelely and
Keely behind them, and before he could say knife, they had whisked the trays
and a couple of small tables into the parlor, and set out everything aresh.
Gandalf sat at the head of the party with the 13 dwarves all round, and Bilbo
sat on a stool at the fireside, nibbling at a biscuit. His appetite was quite
taken away, and trying to look as if this was all perfectly ordinary and not
in the least an adventure. The dwarves ate and ate and talked and talked, and
time got on. At last they pushed their chairs back, and Bilbo made a move to
collect the plates and glasses.
I suppose you will all stay to supper, he said in his politest, unpressing tones.
Of course, said Thoren, and after we sh get through the business till late, and
we must have some music first, now to clear up. Thereupon the 12 dwarves, not
Thoren. He was too important, and stayed talking to Gandalf jumped to their feet,
and made tall piles of all the things.
Off they went, not waiting for trays, balancing columns of plates, each with a
bottle on the top, with one hand, while the hobbit ran after them, almost
squeaking with fright. Please be careful, and please don't trouble. I can
manage. But the dwarves only started to sing. Chip the glasses and crack the
plates. Blunt the knives and bend the forks. That's what Bilbo Baggins hates.
Smash the bottles and burn the corks.
Cut the cloth and tread on the fat. Pour the milk on the pantry floor. Leave the
bones on the bedroom mat. Splash the wine on every door. Dump the crocs in a
boiling bowl. Pound them up with a thumping bowl. And when you finished, if
any are whole, send them down the hall to roll.
That's what Bilbo Baggins hates. So carefully, carefully with the plates.
And of course they did none of these dreadful things, and everything was
cleaned and put away safe as quick as lightning, while the hobbit was turning
round and round in the middle of the kitchen, trying to see what they were
doing. Then they went back and found Thoren with his feet on the fenders,
smoking a pipe. He was blowing the most enormous smoke rings, and wherever he
told one to go, it went up the chimney, or behind the clock, on the mantlepiece,
or under the table, or round and round the ceiling. But wherever it went, it
was not quick enough to escape Gandalf.
Pop! He sent a smaller smoke ring from his short clay pipe straight through
each one of Thoren's. Then Gandalf's smoke ring would go green and come back
to hover over the wizard's head. He had a cloud of them about him already, and
in the dim light it made him look strange and sorcerous.
Bilbo stood still and watched. He loved smoke rings, and then he blushed to
think how proud he had been yesterday morning of the smoke rings he had sent
up the wind over the hill. "Now for some music," said Thorin. "Bring out the instruments."
Kelly and Fely rushed for their bags and brought back little fiddles. Dory, Nori,
and Aie brought up flutes from somewhere inside their coats. Balmore produced a
drum from the hall. Bifur and Bofer went out, too, and came back with clarinets
that they had left among the walking sticks.
Wallan and Balon said, "Excuse me, I left mine in the porch." "Just bring
mine in with you," said Thoren. They came back with files as big as
themselves, and with Thoren's harp wrapped in a green cloth. It was a
beautiful golden harp, and when Thoren struck it, the music began all at once,
so sudden and sweet that Bilbo forgot everything else, and was swept away into
dark lands under strange moons, far over the water, and very far from his hobbit hole under
the hill. The dark came into the room from the little window that opened in
the side of the hill. The fire light flickered. It was April and still. They
played on while the shadow of Gandalf's beard wagged against the wall. The dark
filled all the room and the fire died down and the shadows were lost and still
they played on. And suddenly first one and then another began to sing as they
played. Deepthroated singing of the dwarves in the deep places of their
ancient homes. And this is like a fragment of their song, if it can be
like their song without their music. Far over the misty mountains cold to
dungeons deep and caverns old we must away air break of day to seek the pale
enchanted gold. The dwarves of Yor made mighty spells while hammers fell like
ringing bells in places deep where dark things sleep in hollow halls beneath the
fells. For ancient king and elvish lord, there many a gleaming golden horde. They
shaped and wrought, and light they caught to hide in gems on hilt of sword.
On silver necklaces they strung, the flowering stars on crowns they hung the
dragon fire in twisted wire. They meshed the light of moon and sun. Far over the
misty mountains cold to dungeons deep and caverns old we must away airbreak of
day to claim our longforgotten gold.
Goblets they carve there for themselves.
And harps of gold where no man delves there lay they long. And many a song was
sung unheard by men or elves.
The pines were roaring on the height.
The winds were moaning in the night. The fire was red if flaming spread. The
trees like torches blazed with light.
The bells were ringing in the dale, and men looked up with faces pale. The
dragons eye more fierce than fire laid low their towers and houses frail. The
mountain smoked beneath the moon. The dwarves they heard the of doom.
They fled their hall to dying fall beneath his feet beneath the moon. Far
over the misty mountains grim to dungeons deep in caverns dim we must
away air break of day to win our harps and gold from him. As they sang the
hobbit felt the love of beautiful things made by hands and by cunning and by
magic moving through him. A fierce and a jealous love, the desire of the hearts
of dwarves. Then something Tukish woke up inside him, and he wished to go and
see the great mountains, and hear the pine trees and the waterfalls, and
explore the caves, and wear a sword instead of a walking stick. He looked
out of the window. The stars were out in a dark sky above the trees. He thought
of the jewels of the dwarves shining in dark caverns, suddenly in the wood beyond.
The water of flame leapt up, probably somebody lighting a woodf fire, and he
thought of plundering dragons settling on his quiet hill and kindling it all to
flames. He shuddered, and very quickly he was playing Mr. Baggins of Bagand
Underhill again. He got up trembling. He had less than half a mind to fetch the
lamp, and more than half a mind to pretend to, and go and hide behind the
beer barrels in the cellar, and not come out again until all the dwarves had gone
away. Suddenly he found that the music and the singing had stopped, and they
were all looking at him with eyes shining in the dark. "Where are you
going?" said Thoren, in a tone that seemed to show that he guessed both
halves of the hobbit's mind. What about a little light? said Bobo apologetically.
We like the dark, said all the dwarves.
Dark for dark business. There are many hours before dawn.
Of course, said Bilbo, and sat down in a hurry. He missed the stool and sat in
the fender, knocking over the poker and shovel with a crash.
Hush, said Gandalf. Let Thoren speak.
And this is how Thoren began.
Gandalf, dwarves, and Mr. Baggins, we are met together in the house of our
friend and fellow conspirator, this most excellent and audacious hobbit. May the
hair on his toes never fall out. All praise to his wine and ale. He paused
for breath and for a polite remark from the hobbit, but the compliments were
quite lost on poor Bilbo Baggins, who was wagging his mouth in protest at
being called audacious and worst of all fellow conspirator. Though no noise came
out, he was so flumxed. So Thoren went on. We are met to discuss our plans, our
ways, means, policy, and devices. We shall soon, before the break of day,
start on our long journey, a journey from which some of us, or perhaps all of
us, except our friend and counselor, the ingenious wizard Gandalf, may never
return. It is a solemn moment. Our object is, I take it, well known to us
all. To the estimable Mr. Baggins, and perhaps to one or two of the younger
dwarfs, I think I should be right in naming Killy and Philly, for instance.
The exact situation at the moment may require a little brief explanation.
This was Thor in style. He was an important dwarf. If he had been allowed,
he would probably have gone on like this until he was out of breath, without
telling anyone there anything that was not known already. But he was rudely interrupted.
Poor Bilbo couldn't bear it any longer.
Let's see why he's so easy. All the dwarves sprang up, knocking over the
table. Gandalf struck a blue light on the end of his magic staff, and in its
firework glare, the poor little hobbit could be seen kneeling on the hearth
rug, shaking like a jelly that was melting. Then he fell flat on the floor
and kept on calling out struck by lightning, struck by lightning, over and
over again. And that was all they could get out of him for a long time. So they
took him and laid him out of the way on the drawing room sofa with a drink at
his elbow, and they went back to their dark business. "Excitable little
fellow," said Gandalf, as they sat down again. "Gets funny queer fits, but he is
one of the best. One of the best as fierce as a dragon in a pinch. If you
have ever seen a dragon in a pinch, you will realize that this was only poetical
exaggeration applied to any hobbit, even to old Tuk's great grand uncle Bulrare,
who was so huge for a hobbit, that he could ride a horse. He charged the ranks
of the goblins of Mount Graham in the Battle of the Green Fields, and knocked
their king Gimu's head clean off with a wooden club. It sailed a 100 yards
through the air and went down a rabbit hole, and in this way the battle was
won, and the game of golf invented at the same moment. In the meanwhile,
however, Bulroaru's gentler descendant was reviving in the drawing room. After
a while, and a drink, he crept nervously to the door of the parlor. This is what
he heard. Glowing speaking, humph, or some snort, more or less like that. Will
he do, do you think? It is all very well for Gandalf to talk about this hobbit
being fierce, but one shriek like that in a moment of excitement would be
enough to wake the dragon and all his relatives and kill the lot of us. I
think it sounded more like fright than excitement. In fact, if it had not been
for the sign on the door, I should have been sure we had come to the wrong
house. As soon as I clapped eyes on the little fellow bobbing and puffing on the
mat, I had my doubts. He looks more like a grosser than a burglar.
Then Mr. Baggins turned the handle and went in. The took side had won. He
suddenly felt he would go without bed and breakfast to be thought fierce. As
for little fellow bobbing on the mat, it almost made him really fierce. Many a
time afterwards the bag and pot regretted what he did now and he said to
himself, "Bilbo, you were a fool. You walked right in and put your foot in
it." "Pardon me," he said, "if I have overheard words that you were saying. I
don't pretend to understand what you are talking about or your reference to
burglars, but I think I am right in believing this is what he called being
on his dignity, that you think I am no good. I will show you. I have no signs
on my door. It was painted a week ago,
and I am quite sure you have come to the
wrong house. As soon as I saw your funny faces on the doorstep, I had my doubts,
but treat it as the right one. Tell me
what you want done, and I will try it if
I have to walk from here to the east of east and fight the wild wereworms in the
last desert.
I had a great great great grand uncle once, Bullroar took. And yes, yes, but
that was long ago, said Gloin. I was talking about you, and I assure you
there is a mark on this store, the usual one in the trade, or used to be. Burglar
wants a good job, plenty of excitement, and reasonable reward. That's how it is
usually read. You can say expert treasure hunter instead of burglar if
you like. Some of them do. It's all the same to us. Gandalf told us that there
was a man of the sort in these parts looking for a job at once and that he
had arranged for a meeting here this Wednesday tea time. Of course there is a
mark, said Gandalf. I put it there myself for very good reasons. You asked
me to find the 14th man for your expedition, and I choose Mr. Baggins.
Just let anyone say I chose the wrong man or the wrong house, and you can stop
at 13 and have all the bad luck you like, or go back to digging coal. He
scowlled so angrily at Glowin that the dwarf huddled back in his cheer. And
when Bilbo tried to open his mouth to ask a question, he turned and frowned at
him and stuck out his bushy eyebrows till Bilbo shut his mouth tight with a
snap. That's right, said Gandalf. Let's have no more argument. I have chosen Mr.
Baggins, and that ought to be enough for
all of you. If I say he is a burglar, a
burglar he is, or will be when the time comes. There is a lot more in him than
you guess, and a deal more than he has any idea of himself. You may possibly
all live to thank me yet. Now, Bilbo, my boy, fetch the lamp, and let's have a
little light on this. On the table, in the light of a big lamp with a red
shade, he spread a piece of parchment rather like a map. This was made by
Thor, your grandfather, Thorin, he said in answer to the dwarf's excited
questions. It is a plan of the mountain.
I don't see that this will help us much, said Thoren disappointedly after a
glance. I remember the mountain well enough and the lands about it, and I
know where Murkwood is, and the withered heath, where the great dragons bred.
"There is a dragon marked in red on the mountain," said Balon, "but it will be
easy enough to find him without that, if ever we arrive there." "There is one
point that you haven't noticed," said the wizard, "and that is the secret
entrance. You see that rune on the west side and the hand pointing to it from
the other runes that marks a hidden passage to the lower halls. Look at the
map at the beginning of this book and you will see there the runes.
It may have been secret once, said Thoren. But how do we know that it is
secret any longer? Old Smal has lived there long enough now to find out
anything there is to know about those caves.
He may, but he can't have used it for years and years.
Why? Because it is too small. 5 ft high the door and three may walk a breast,
say the runes. But Smal could not creep into a hole that size, not even when he
was a young dragon. Certainly not after devouring so many of the dwarves and men
of Dale. It seems a great big hole to me, squeaked Bilbo, who had no
experience of dragons, and only of hobbit holes. He was getting excited and
interested again, so that he forgot to keep his mouth shut. He loved maps, and
in his hall there hung a large one of the country round, with all his favorite
walks marked on it in red ink. How could such a large door be kept secret from
everybody outside, apart from the dragon, he asked. He was only a little
hobbit, you must remember.
In lots of ways, said Gandalf. But in what way this one has been hidden, we
don't know without going to see. From what it says on the map, I should guess
there is a closed door which has been made to look exactly like the side of
the mountain. That is the usual dwarf's method. I think that is right, isn't it?
Quite right, said Doran. Also, went on Gandalf, I forgot to mention that with
the map went a key, a small and curious key. Here it is, he said, and handed to
Thoren a key with a long barrel and intricate wards made of silver. Keep it safe.
Indeed, I will, said Thoren, and he fastened it upon a fine chain that hung
about his neck and under his jacket. Now things begin to look more hopeful. This
news alters them much for the better. So far, we have had no clear idea what to
do. We thought of going east, as quiet and careful as we could, as far as the
long lake. After that, the trouble would begin. A long time before that, if I
know anything about the roads east, interrupted Gandalf.
We might go from there up along the river running, went on Thorin, taking no
notice, and so to the ruins of Dale, the old town in the valley there, under the
shadow of the mountain. But we none of us like the idea of the front gate. The
river runs right out of it through the great cliff at the south of the
mountain, and out of it comes the dragon too far too often, unless he has changed
his habits. That would be no good, said the wizard. Not without a mighty
warrior, even a hero. I tried to find one, but warriors are busy fighting one
another in distant lands, and in this neighborhood heroes are scarce or simply
not to be found. Swords in these parts are mostly blunt, and axes are used for
trees, and shields as cradles or dish covers, and dragons are comfortably far
off, and therefore legendary. That is why I settled on burglary, especially
when I remembered the existence of a side door. And here is our little Bilbo
Baggins, the burglar, the chosen and selected burglar. So now, let's get on and make some plans.
Very well then, said Thoren, supposing the burglar expert gives us some ideas or suggestions.
He turned with mock politess to Bilbo.
First I should like to know a bit more about things, said he, feeling all
confused and a bit shaky inside, but so far still tookly determined to go on
with things. I mean about the gold and the dragon and all that, and how it got
there, and who it belongs to, and so on and further.
Bless me, said Thoren. Haven't you got a map? And didn't you hear our song? And
haven't we been talking about all this for hours?
All the same, I should like it all plain and clear, said he obstinately, putting
on his business manner, usually reserved for people who tried to borrow money off
him, and doing his best to appear wise and prudent and professional, and live
up to Gandalf's recommendation. Also, I should like to know about risks,
out-ofpocket expenses, time required, and remuneration, and so forth. By which
he meant, what am I going to get out of
it, and am I going to come back alive?"
"Oh, very well," said Thoren. "Long ago, in my grandfather throws time, our
family was driven out of the far north, and came back with all their wealth and
their tools to this mountain on the map.
It had been discovered by my foreign ancestor, trained the old, but now they
mined and they tunnneled and they made huder holes and greater workshops, and
in addition, I believe they found a good deal of gold and a great many jewels,
too. Anyway, they grew immensely rich and famous, and my grandfather was king
under the mountain again, and treated with great reverence by the mortal men
who lived to the south, and were gradually spreading up the running river
as far as the valley, overshadowed by the mountain. They built the merry town
of Dale there. In those days, kings used to send for our smiths and reward even
the least skillful most richly. Fathers would beg us to take their sons as
apprentices and pay us handsomely, especially in food supplies, which we
never bothered to grow or find for ourselves. Altogether those were good
days for us, and the poorest of us had money to spend and to lend, and leisure
to make beautiful things just for the fun of it, not to speak of the most
marvelous and magical toys, the like of which is not to be found in the world nowadays.
So my grandfather's halls became full of armor and jewels and carvings and cups,
and the toy market of Dale was the wonder of the north. Undoubtedly, that
was what brought the dragon. Dragons steal gold and jewels you know from men
and elves and dwarves wherever they can find them and they guard their plunder
as long as they live which is practically forever unless they are
killed and never enjoy a brass ring of it. Indeed they hardly know a good bit
of work from a bad though they usually have a good notion of the current market
value and they can't make a thing for themselves not even men a little loose
scale of their armor. There were lots of dragons in the north in those days, and
gold was probably getting scarce up there, with the dwarves flying south or
getting killed, and all the general waste and destruction that dragons make
going from bad to worse. There was a most specially greedy, strong, and
wicked worm called Smog. One day he flew up into the air and came south. The
first we heard of it was a noise like a hurricane coming from the north and the
pine trees on the mountain creaking and cracking in the wind. Some of the
dwarves who happened to be outside. I was one luckily a fine adventurous lad
in those days, always wandering about, and it saved my life that day. Well,
from a good way off we saw the dragon settle on our mountain in a spout of
flame. Then he came down the slopes and when he reached the woods they all went
up in fire. By that time all the bells were ringing and Dale and the warriors
were arming. The dwarves rushed out of their great gate. But there was the
dragon waiting for them. None escaped that way. The river rushed up in steam
and a fog fell on Dale. And in the fog the dragon came on them and destroyed
most of the warriors. The usual unhappy story. It was only too common in those
days. Then he went back and crept in through the front gate and routed out
all the halls and lanes and tunnels, alleys, cellars, mansions and passages.
After that there were no dwarves left alive inside, and he took all their
wealth for himself. Probably, for that is the dragon's way. He is piled it all
up in a great heap far inside, and sleeps on it for a bed. Later he used to
crawl out of the great gate and come by night to Dale and carry away people
especially maidens to eat until Dale was ruined and all the people dead are gone.
What goes on there now I don't know for certain but I don't suppose anyone lives
nearer to the mountain than the far edge of the long lake nowadays.
The few of us that were well outside sat and wept in hiding and cursed smal. And
there we were unexpectedly joined by my father and my grandfather with singed
beards. They looked very grim, but they said very little. When I asked how they
had got away, they told me to hold my tongue and said that one day in the
proper time I should know. After that we went away, and we have had to earn our
livingings as best we could up and down the lands, often enough sinking as low
as blacksmith work or even coal mining.
But we have never forgotten our stolen treasure. And even now, when I will
allow, we have a good bit laid by, and are not so badly off. Here Thoren
stroked the gold chain round his neck.
We still mean to get it back, and to bring our curses home to Smug, if we
can. I have often wondered about my fathers and my grandfather's escape. I
see now they must have had a private side door which only they knew about.
But apparently they made a map and I should like to know how Gandalf got hold
of it and why it did not come down to me
the rightful heir. I did not get hold of it. I was given it said the wizard. Your
grandfather Thor was killed you remember in the minds of Moria by Azov the
goblin. Curse his name. Yes, said Thorin. and Thra, your father, went away
on the 21st of April, a 100red years ago last Thursday, and has never been seen
by you since." "True, true," said Thorin. "Well, your father gave me this
to give to you, and if I have chosen my own time and way for handing it over,
you can hardly blame me, considering the trouble I had to find you." Your father
could not remember his own name when he gave me the paper, and he never told me
yours. So on the whole I think I ought to be praised and thanked. Here it is,
said he, handing the map to Thoren. I don't understand, said Thoren, and Bilbo
felt he would have liked to say the same. The explanation did not seem to
explain. Your grandfather, said the wizard slowly and grimly, gave the map
to his son for safety before he went to the mines of Moria. Your father went
away to try his luck with the map after your grandfather was killed, and lots of
adventures of a most unpleasant sort he had, but he never got near the mountain.
How he got there, I don't know, but I found him a prisoner in the dungeons of
the necromancer.
Whatever you're doing there, asked Doran with a shudder, and all the dwarves
shivered. Never you mind. I was finding things out as usual. At a nasty,
dangerous business it was. Even I, Gandalf, only just escaped. I tried to
save your father, but it was too late.
He was witless and wandering, and had forgotten almost everything except the
map and the key. We have long ago paid the goblins of Moria, said Thoren. We
must give a thought to the necromancer.
Don't be absurd. He is an enemy far beyond the powers of all the doors put
together. If they could all be collected again from the four corners of the
world. The one thing your father wished was for his son to read the map and use
the key. The dragon and the mountain are more than big enough tasks for you.
Here. Here, said Bilbo, and accidentally said it aloud. Here what? they all said
turning suddenly towards him and he was so flustered that he answered what I have got to say.
What's that? They asked. Well, I should say that you ought to go east and have a
look round. After all, there is the side door and dragons must sleep sometimes, I
suppose. If you sit on the doorstep long enough, I dare say you will think of
something. And well, don't you know, I think we have talked long enough for one
night, if you see what I mean. What about bed and an early start and all
that? I will give you a good breakfast before you go. Before we go, I suppose
you mean, said Thoren. Archie the burglar, and isn't sitting on the
doorstep your job not to speak of getting inside the door? But I agree
about bed and breakfast. I like six eggs with my ham when starting on a journey,
fried not poached, and mind you, don't break them. After all the others had
ordered their breakfasts without so much as a please, which annoyed Bilbo very
much, they all got up. The hobbit had to find room for them all and filled all
his spare rooms and made beds on chairs and sofas before he got them all stowed
and went to his own little bed, very tired and not altogether happy. One
thing he did make his mind up about was not to bother to get up very early and
cook everybody else's wretched breakfast. The Turkishness was wearing
off, and he was not now quite so sure that he was going on any journey in the
morning. As he lay in bed, he could hear Thoren still humming to himself in the
best bedroom next to him. Far over the misty mountains, cold to dungeons deep
in caverns old we must away air break of day to find our long-forgotten gold.
Bilbo went to sleep with that in his ears, and it gave him very uncomfortable
dreams. It was long after the break of day when he woke up. Chapter 2. Roast